<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Welcome to the Data Science in Physics Research Lab on Data Science in Physics Lab</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Welcome to the Data Science in Physics Research Lab on Data Science in Physics Lab</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>© 2025 </copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 29 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>BMFTR Funds DEMOS</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/bmftr-demos/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/bmftr-demos/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;re happy to announce that the BMFTR has funded the DEMOS project as part of the ErUM-Data Call. The overall project is coordinated by Prof. Mikhail Mikhasenko at the University of Bochum. We will contribute jointly with Philipp Eller from Elisa Resconi&amp;rsquo;s research group.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>BMFTR Funds SciFM</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/bmftr-scifm/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/bmftr-scifm/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;re happy to announce that the BMFTR is funding a new Germany-wide effort “SciFM” to develop foundation models in astro- and particle physics. Our group will be part of the Munich hub together with the group of Daniel Grün at the LMU.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 class=&#34;relative group&#34;&gt;SciFM: Big Models for Big Science
    &lt;div id=&#34;scifm-big-models-for-big-science&#34; class=&#34;anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    
    &lt;span
        class=&#34;absolute top-0 w-6 transition-opacity opacity-0 -start-6 not-prose group-hover:opacity-100 select-none&#34;&gt;
        &lt;a class=&#34;text-primary-300 dark:text-neutral-700 !no-underline&#34; href=&#34;#scifm-big-models-for-big-science&#34; aria-label=&#34;Anchor&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;
    
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A major unsolved problem in Fundamental Physics is that even the best theories in physics - the Standard Models of Cosmology and Particle Physics - only explain a fraction of the Universe: 95% of the energy in the Universe appears to be either “dark matter” or “dark energy”. What are they exactly? Currently physicists can only speculate what the laws of nature look like that explain these phenomena.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Job Opportunities</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/jobs/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/jobs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;If you are interested in joining our group please check out the openings below. If there are no current openings you can still reach out to us to see whether we expect to have any openings in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are always interested in taking on students for Master and Bachelor thesis projects or via some of the other TUM student opportunitie such as TUM IDPs, the TUM Data Innovation Lab or Guided Research projects.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lukas Heinrich awarded ERC Starting Grant</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/erc-stg-lukas-heinrich/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/erc-stg-lukas-heinrich/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Big grant news today! I feel very lucky and honored for this opportunity from European Research Council (ERC) We will attempt to go for a big qualitative step up in how we use AI/ML to predict how particles interact with matter. Stoked to get started on this in 2026. we will release job advertisements soon!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>NeurIPS ML4PS Workshop</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/neurips/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/neurips/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A number of people from our group will be attending the NeurIPS Workshop on Machine Learning for Natural Sciences. Nicole Hartman is part of the organizing team and Matthias Vigl will present his double descent work during the workshop. If you&amp;rsquo;re arround don&amp;rsquo;t hesistate to get in touch!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New Paper: Double Descent in Particle Physics Data</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/double-descent-paper/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/double-descent-paper/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;re happy to announce a new paper from our research lab. The paper is the first to discover and invesitgate the &amp;ldquo;Double Descent Phenomenon&amp;rdquo; in particle physics data. Check it out! &lt;a
  href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.01397&#34;
    target=&#34;_blank&#34;
  &gt;https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.01397&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 class=&#34;relative group&#34;&gt;Abstract
    &lt;div id=&#34;abstract&#34; class=&#34;anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    
    &lt;span
        class=&#34;absolute top-0 w-6 transition-opacity opacity-0 -start-6 not-prose group-hover:opacity-100 select-none&#34;&gt;
        &lt;a class=&#34;text-primary-300 dark:text-neutral-700 !no-underline&#34; href=&#34;#abstract&#34; aria-label=&#34;Anchor&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;
    
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently, the benefit of heavily overparameterized models has been observed in machine learning tasks: models with enough capacity to easily cross the interpolation threshold improve in generalization error compared to the classical bias-variance tradeoff regime. We demonstrate this behavior for the first time in particle physics data and explore when and where ‘double descent’ appears and under which circumstances overparameterization results in a performance gain.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New Paper: maria goes NIFTy</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/nifty-maria-paper/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/nifty-maria-paper/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;re happy to announce a new paper from our research lab. The paper applies the NifTY reconstruction algorithm to new types of telescope data. From our group Jonas Würzinger and Richard Fuchs were involed. The project was a part of our ODSL efforts. Check it out: &lt;a
  href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.01600&#34;
    target=&#34;_blank&#34;
  &gt;https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.01600&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 class=&#34;relative group&#34;&gt;Abstract
    &lt;div id=&#34;abstract&#34; class=&#34;anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    
    &lt;span
        class=&#34;absolute top-0 w-6 transition-opacity opacity-0 -start-6 not-prose group-hover:opacity-100 select-none&#34;&gt;
        &lt;a class=&#34;text-primary-300 dark:text-neutral-700 !no-underline&#34; href=&#34;#abstract&#34; aria-label=&#34;Anchor&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;
    
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Sub-)millimetre single-dish telescopes feature faster mapping speeds and access larger spatial scales than their interferometric counterparts. However, atmospheric fluctuations tend to dominate their signals and complicate recovery of the astronomical sky. Here we develop a framework for Gaussian process-based sky reconstruction and separation of the atmospheric emission from the astronomical signal based on Numerical Information Field Theory (\texttt{NIFTy}). To validate this novel approach, we use the \textit{maria} software to generate synthetic time-ordered observational data mimicking the MUSTANG-2 bolometric array. This approach leads to significantly improved sky reconstructions versus traditional methods.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Kristian Tchiorny starts PhD</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/kristian-phd-start/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/kristian-phd-start/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;re happy to share that Kristian Tchiorny is starting a PhD in our group. He will be working on a project funded by the SFB1258 on the AI-driven design optimization of neutrino telescopes. In particularm, we will be developing strategies to optimize the planned P-ONE neutrino telescope. The work will be closely coordinated with Elisa Resconi&amp;rsquo;s group.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Richard Hildebrandt starts PhD</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/richard-phd-start/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/richard-phd-start/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;After completing his Master Thesis on parton density functions, Richard Hildebrandt is joining our group to pursue his doctral degree. He will work on foundation models in partilce physics.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Excellence Cluster ORIGINS approved for a second funding period</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/origins_approved/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/origins_approved/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Excellence Cluster ORIGINS was approved for a second funding period! This is close to our heart, as our research group and the ORIGINS Data Science Lab is a direct outcome of the first funding period. We&amp;rsquo;re now expanding the ODSL with a second co-coordinator (Daniel Grün) and an expanded team of researchers. Keep an eye out for job postings!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check it out: &lt;a
  href=&#34;https://www.origins-cluster.de&#34;
    target=&#34;_blank&#34;
  &gt;https://www.origins-cluster.de&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SFB 1258 approved for third funding period</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/sfb_approved/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/sfb_approved/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Great news! The Collaborative Research Center (Sonderforschungsbereich) SFB1258 was approved for a third funding period. Out group is involved in three exciting projects in collaboration with Andreas Weiler and Uli Haisch, Elisa Resconi and Laura Fabbietti.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check it out: &lt;a
  href=&#34;https://www.sfb1258.de&#34;
    target=&#34;_blank&#34;
  &gt;https://www.sfb1258.de&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project Students</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/projectstudents/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/projectstudents/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We are always happy to take on project students if we can find a good topic to work on. Please do not hesistate to reach out if you&amp;rsquo;re interested in our research program.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 class=&#34;relative group&#34;&gt;TUM IDPs
    &lt;div id=&#34;tum-idps&#34; class=&#34;anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    
    &lt;span
        class=&#34;absolute top-0 w-6 transition-opacity opacity-0 -start-6 not-prose group-hover:opacity-100 select-none&#34;&gt;
        &lt;a class=&#34;text-primary-300 dark:text-neutral-700 !no-underline&#34; href=&#34;#tum-idps&#34; aria-label=&#34;Anchor&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;
    
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;IDP is an interdisciplinary project program offered by the TUM Computer Science program. Here, students work with researchers in applied doains on a technical project.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Writing a BSc / MSc Thesis with our Group</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/theses/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/theses/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Our group is always looking for students that are excited about our research program and want to prepare a thesis on a particular research topic with us. We often have a range of projects already in mind but are also interested in topics that the students bring to us on their own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 class=&#34;relative group&#34;&gt;Potential Thesis Topics
    &lt;div id=&#34;potential-thesis-topics&#34; class=&#34;anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    
    &lt;span
        class=&#34;absolute top-0 w-6 transition-opacity opacity-0 -start-6 not-prose group-hover:opacity-100 select-none&#34;&gt;
        &lt;a class=&#34;text-primary-300 dark:text-neutral-700 !no-underline&#34; href=&#34;#potential-thesis-topics&#34; aria-label=&#34;Anchor&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;
    
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Searches for Beyond Standard Model Physics with ATLAS&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Higgs Physics with ATLAS&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reinterpretation Tools for High Energy Physics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;AI methods for Fundamental Physics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Statistical Modelling and Inference&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Distributed Computing and large-scale data science tools&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Simulation-Baesd Inference for FUndamental Physics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;AI-driven experiment design&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 class=&#34;relative group&#34;&gt;External Thesis Supervision
    &lt;div id=&#34;external-thesis-supervision&#34; class=&#34;anchor&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    
    &lt;span
        class=&#34;absolute top-0 w-6 transition-opacity opacity-0 -start-6 not-prose group-hover:opacity-100 select-none&#34;&gt;
        &lt;a class=&#34;text-primary-300 dark:text-neutral-700 !no-underline&#34; href=&#34;#external-thesis-supervision&#34; aria-label=&#34;Anchor&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;
    
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As our group specialized in methods research we sometimes also act as formal supervisors to data science-related thesis that are carried out in collaboration with other research organizations or industry. If you&amp;rsquo;re thinking about such an external thesis, please get in touch explaining your data-science related topic.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
